Guide to the Ralph W. Tyler Papers 1932-1988
University of Chicago Library
- Series III: Correspondence
  - Subseries 3: Correspondence 1981-1988
    - Education & Modern Languages (Box 51, Folder 19)
    - Education Commission of the States (Box 51, Folder 20)
    - Education Network for Older Adults (Box 51, Folder 21)
    - Educational Leadership (Box 51, Folder 22)
    - Educational Products Information Exchange (EPIE) Institute (Box 51, Folder 23)
    - Educational Researcher (Box 51, Folder 24)
    - Educational Technology Publications (Box 51, Folder 25)
    - Educational Testing Service (Box 51, Folder 26)
    - Elms College (Box 51, Folder 27)
    - Emeritus, Inc. (Box 51, Folder 28)
    - Emory University (Box 51, Folder 29)
    - Excellence in Teaching (Box 51, Folder 30)
    - Expenses (Box 51, Folder 31)
    - Exxon Education Foundation (Box 51, Folder 32)
    - F, correspondence (Box 51, Folder 33)
    - Family Focus - Life Lab Science Programs (Box 51, Folder 34)
    - Florida Association of College and Universities Newsletter (Box 51, Folder 35)
    - George Washington University (Box 51, Folder 36)
    - Georgia Educational Leadership (Box 51, Folder 37)
    - H, correspondence (Box 51, Folder 38)
    - Hart, Leslie (Box 51, Folder 39)
    - Harvard University (Box 51, Folder 40)
    - Hebrew University of Jerusalem (Box 51, Folder 41)
    - Hewlett Foundation (Box 51, Folder 42)
    - Hogg Foundation (Box 51, Folder 43)
    - Honeywell Foundation (Box 51, Folder 44)
    - Hoover Institute on War, Revolution, and Peace (Box 51, Folder 45)
    - Illinois Designated Account Purchase Program (IDAPP) (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - Indiana State University (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - International Encyclopedia of Education (Box 52, Folder 3)
    - International School Services (Box 52, Folder 4)
    - Institute for Educational Leadership (Box 52, Folder 5)
    - Institute for Philosophical Research (Box 52, Folder 6)
    - Institute of Psychoanalysis (Box 52, Folder 7)
    - Institute for Responsive Education (Box 52, Folder 8)
    - Institute for Social Research (Box 52, Folder 9)
    - Institute for Vision Research (Box 52, Folder 10)
    - Institute of Higher Learning (Box 52, Folder 11)
    - Instructor (Box 52, Folder 12)
    - Iowa State University (Box 52, Folder 13)
    - IOX Assessment Associates (Box 52, Folder 14)
    - Itineraries (Box 52, Folder 15)
    - J - I, correspondence (Box 52, Folder 16)
    - Jewish education (Box 52, Folder 17)
    - Jewish Theological Seminary (Box 52, Folder 18)
    - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation (Box 52, Folder 19)
    - Judaica College (Box 52, Folder 20)
    - K, correspondence (Box 52, Folder 21)
    - Kappa Delta Pi (Box 52, Folder 22)
    - Keegan, Frank (Box 52, Folder 23)
    - Kettering Foundation (Box 52, Folder 24)
    - Lambert Associates (Box 52, Folder 25)
    - Lea, Dixie (Box 52, Folder 26)
    - Lock Haven State College (Box 52, Folder 27)
    - Louisiana, State of (Box 52, Folder 28)
    - Loyola University of Chicago (Box 52, Folder 29)
    - M, correspondence (Box 52, Folder 30)
    - MacArthur, John D. and Catherine Foundation (Box 52, Folder 31)
    - Margaret M. Sibley School (Box 52, Folder 32)
    - Merit Scholars (Box 52, Folder 33)
    - Michigan State University (Box 52, Folder 34)
    - Montana Education Board (Box 52, Folder 35)
    - N, correspondence (Box 53, Folder 1)
    - National Academy of Education (Box 53, Folder 2)
    - National Academy of Sciences (Box 53, Folder 3)
    - National Assessment of Educational Progress (Box 53, Folder 4)
    - National Association of State Boards of Education (Box 53, Folder 5)
    - National Center for Atmospheric Research (Box 53, Folder 6)
    - National Commission for Cooperative Education (Box 53, Folder 7)
    - National Commission on Resources for Youth (Box 53, Folder 8)
    - National Foundation for the Improvement of Education (Box 53, Folder 9)
    - National Institute of Economic and Social Research (Box 53, Folder 10)
    - National Science Foundation (Box 53, Folder 11)
    - National Society for the Study of Education (Box 53, Folder 11a)
    - National Student/Parent Mock Election, 1984 (Box 53, Folder 12)
    - Nebraska, State of (Box 53, Folder 13)
    - New Jersey, State of (Box 53, Folder 14)
    - New Mexico State University (Box 53, Folder 15)
    - New School for Social Research (Box 53, Folder 16)
    - New York State Educational Conference Board (Box 53, Folder 17)
    - New York University (Box 53, Folder 18)
    - North Carolina State University (Box 53, Folder 19)
    - Northeastern University (Box 53, Folder 20)
    - Northern Illinois University (Box 53, Folder 21)
    - Northwestern University (Box 53, Folder 22)
    - Ohio State University (Box 53, Folder 23)
    - Oklahoma State University (Box 53, Folder 24)
    - Ontario Council of Graduate Studies (Box 53, Folder 25)
    - P, correspondence (Box 53, Folder 26)
    - Paideia Proposal (Box 53, Folder 27)
    - Palo Alto Medical Foundation (Box 53, Folder 28)
    - Parent Participation TV Workshop Project (Box 53, Folder 29)
    - Pedamorphosis, Inc. (Box 53, Folder 30)
    - Pennsylvania State University (Box 53, Folder 31)
    - Pepperdine University (Box 53, Folder 32)
    - Pergamon Press, Ltd. (Box 53, Folder 33)
    - Phi Delta Kappa (Box 53, Folder 34)
    - Purdue University (Box 53, Folder 35)
    - Q correspondence (Box 54, Folder 1)
    - Questioning Exchange (Box 54, Folder 2)
    - R, correspondence (Box 54, Folder 3)
    - Rand Corporation (Box 54, Folder 4)
    - Research in Higher Learning (Box 54, Folder 5)
    - Rhode Island & Providence Plantations, State of (Box 54, Folder 6)
    - Robert Morris College (Box 54, Folder 7)
    - Rochester Institute of Technology (Box 54, Folder 8)
    - Rosenthal, Bernard (Box 54, Folder 9)
    - S, correspondence (Box 54, Folder 10)
    - San Francisco State University (Box 54, Folder 11)
    - Schwab, Joseph J. (Box 54, Folder 12)
    - Schools (districts, counties, cities, and boards) (Box 54, Folder 13)
    - Southern Association of Colleges and Schools (Box 54, Folder 14)
    - Spencer Foundation (Box 54, Folder 15)
    - Stanford University (Box 54, Folder 16)
    - State University of New York (SUNY) (Box 54, Folder 17)
    - Steller, Arthur (Box 54, Folder 18)
    - Stetson University (Box 54, Folder 19)
    - Syracuse University (Box 54, Folder 20)
    - T, correspondence (Box 54, Folder 21)
    - Taxpayers' Foundation (Box 54, Folder 22)
    - Teachers' Guide to Television (Box 54, Folder 23)
    - Thomas Jefferson Research Center (Box 54, Folder 24)
    - Trinity University (Box 54, Folder 25)
    - United States Department of Agriculture (Box 54, Folder 26)
    - United States Department of Education (Box 54, Folder 27)
    - United States Senate Democratic Leadership Circle (Box 54, Folder 28)
    - Universities (various) (Box 54, Folder 29)
    - University of Alabama (Box 54, Folder 30)
    - University of California (all) (Box 54, Folder 31)
    - University of Chicago (Box 54, Folder 32)
    - University of Hamburg (Box 54, Folder 33)
    - University of Illinois (all) (Box 54, Folder 34)
    - University of Kansas (Box 55, Folder 1)
    - University of Lowell (Box 55, Folder 2)
    - University of Maryland (Box 55, Folder 3)
    - University of Massachusetts (Box 55, Folder 4)
    - University of Massachusetts, Advisory Committee packet (Box 55, Folder 5)
    - University of Michigan (Box 55, Folder 6)
    - University of Nebraska (Box 55, Folder 7)
    - University of North Carolina (Box 55, Folder 8)
    - University of Pennsylvania (Box 55, Folder 9)
    - University of Pittsburgh (Box 55, Folder 10)
    - University of South Carolina (Box 55, Folder 11)
    - University of Southern California (Box 55, Folder 12)
    - University of Southern Mississippi (Box 55, Folder 13)
    - University of Texas (all) (Box 55, Folder 14)
    - University of West Florida (Box 55, Folder 15)
    - University of Wisconsin (Box 55, Folder 16)
    - University of Wyoming (Box 55, Folder 17)
    - Utah State University (Box 55, Folder 18)
    - W, correspondence (Box 55, Folder 19)
    - W. Clement and Jessie V. Stone Foundation (Box 55, Folder 20)
    - Western Michigan University (Box 55, Folder 21)
    - William and Flora Hewlett Foundation (Box 55, Folder 22)
    - Wilson Center (Box 55, Folder 23)
    - Yale University (Box 55, Folder 24)
- Series IV: Writings by Tyler
  - Subseries 1: Bibliography
    - Ralph W. Tyler; A Bibliography 1929-1986 (bound) (Box 56, Folder 1)
    - Supplement to Ralph W. Tyler; A Bibliography 1929-1986 with complete citations to published works. (Box 56, Folder 1a)
  - Subseries 2: Periodicals
    - 1929, "New Tests." September 25 "Books to Read." October 9 "New Tests." October 9 "New Tests." October 23 "Books to Read." November 6 "New Tests." November 6 "Books to Read." November 20 "The Choice of Tests." November 20 "In Paper Covers." November 20 "New Tests." November 20 "Books to Read." December 4 "The Need for Adequate Data." December 4 (Box 56, Folder 2)
    - 1930, "In Paper Covers." January 8 "In Paper Covers." January 22 (two reviews) "A Course in History of Education." February 5 "In Paper Covers." February 5 "A Course in History of Education." March 5 "Evaluating the Importance of Teachers' Activities." April "A Plea for Scientists in Education." April 16 "Statistics Needed by Readers." April 16 "New Tests." May 14 "Training Teachers in Service Through Investigations in Teaching." May "The Relation Between the Frequency and the Universality of Teaching Activities." September "Unsuccessful Efforts in Supervision." September 10 "High-School Pupils of Today." October 22 "New Tests." October 22 "Books to Read." November 19 "Editorial Comment." November 19 "Measuring the Ability to Infer." November 19 "A Test of Skill in Using a Microscope." November 19 "What High-School Pupils Forget." November 19 (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - 1931, "Nature of Learning Activities." January "The Master-List as a Device." January 7 "New Tests." January 21 "New Tests." March 4 "What Is Statistical Significance?" March 4 "New Tests." April 1 "A Generalized Technique for Constructing Achievement Tests." April 15 "New Tests." April 15 "New Tests." April 29 "New Tests." May 13 "New Tests." May 27 "Division of Accomplishment Tests." September 16 "New Tests." September 30 "New Tests." October 14 "New Tests." October 28 "New Tests." November 25 "More Valid Measurements of College Work." December "Testing the Ability to Use Scientific Method." No. 3, 1931 (Box 56, Folder 4)
    - 1932, "Ability to Use Scientific Method." January 6 "In Paper Covers." January 6 "New Tests." January 6 "In Paper Covers." January 20 "New Tests." January 20 "Books to Read." February 3 "The Interest Questionnaire." February 3 "In Paper Covers." February 3 "In Paper Covers." February 17 "New Tests." February 17 "Training Courses for Research Workers." March 30 "New Tests." April 27 "In Paper Covers." May 11 "Measuring the Results of College Instruction." May 11 "Books to Read." May 25 "Making a Co-operative Test Service Effective." May 25 "New Tests." May 25 "Division of Accomplishment Tests." October 12 "New Tests." October 26 "Improving Test Materials in the Social Studies." November 9 (Box 56, Folder 5)
    - 1933, "Assumptions Involved in Achievement-Test Construction." February 8 "Permanence of Learning." April "Prevailing Misconceptions; Some Psychological Misconceptions Which Prevent the Better Adjustment of the College Curriculum." June "Tests in Biology." June "Formulating Objectives for Tests." October 11 "New Tests." October 11 "Division of Accomplishment Tests." November 15 "Education and Research at a Mechanics Institute; Measuring Individual Accomplishment." December (Box 56, Folder 6)
    - 1934, "Techniques for Evaluating Behavior." January 17 "New Tests." April 18 "Evaluating Achievement of College Students." May "A Study of the Factors Influencing the Difficulty of Reading Materials for Adults of Limited Reading Ability." July "Some Findings from Studies in the Field of College Biology." October "Testing Ability to Apply Chemical Principles." November "Testing for a Mastery of the Principles of Chemistry." December (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - 1935, "Evaluation; A Challenge and an Opportunity to Progressive Education." January "Evaluation; A Challenge to Progressive Education." January 16 "Progress Report on Evaluation in the Eight-Year Study." December "Achievement Tests in Colleges and Universities." December (Box 56, Folder 8)
    - 1936, "Appraising Progressive Schools." January "Defining and Measuring Objectives of Progressive Education." January "Measuring the Ability to Interpret Experimental Data." February "Division of Accomplishment Tests." October 14 (Box 56, Folder 9)
    - 1937, "The Function of the Evaluation Staff." April "The Summer Workshop." April "The Significance of a Comprehensive Testing Program." April "Evaluation of Student Achievement in the Physical Sciences." June "The Objective Examination; Its Development and Application to Nursing Education." October "Division of Accomplishment Tests." November 10 (Box 56, Folder 10)
    - 1938, "Regarding a Study of the Sciences for General Education." April "An Invitation to teachers of Science." June 4 "Division of Accomplishment Tests." September 21 (Box 56, Folder 11)
    - 1939, "Secondary Curriculum Improvements." February "The Classroom of the Future." June "Comprehensive Evaluation Is an Important Aid to Guidance." September 15 (Box 56, Folder 12)
    - 1940, "Cooperation in the Education of Teachers and Administrators." January "The Education and Adjustment of American Youth; A Symposium and Panel Discussion." July "Educational News and Editorial Comment." September "Educational News and Editorial Comment." November (Box 56, Folder 13)
    - 1941, "Progress Report of the Evaluation Staff." January "Workshops at the University of Chicago." January "Education in Defense of Democracy." March "Contribution of Tests to Research in the Field of Student Personnel Work." April "The Future of American Colleges." April "Place of the Textbook in Modern Education." May "Educational News and Editorial Comment." September "Educational News and Editorial Comment." December (Box 56, Folder 14)
    - 1942, "Educational News and Editorial Comment." February "General Statement on Evaluation." March "Educational News and Editorial Comment." September "Relations of the Urban Community and the Modern School." September "Some Techniques Used in the Follow-Up Study of College Success of Graduates of the Thirty Schools Participating in the Eight-Year Study of the Progressive Education Association." October (Box 56, Folder 15)
    - 1943, "The Importance in Wartime of Co-operation Between Schools and Parents." February "The Role of Education in Our Present Emergency." February "Trends in the Preparation of Teachers." April "Educational News and Editorial Comment." June "Appraisal of Military Training and Experience." July "Educational News and Editorial Comment." September "College Credit for Men in Service." October (Box 56, Folder 16)
    - 1944, "Sound Credit for Military Experience." January "Evaluation of Educational Growth During Military Service." April "Educational News and Editorial Comment." June "Developments in Elementary Education." June 20 "Responsibility of the School for the Improvement of American Life." September "Educational News and Editorial Comment." November (Box 56, Folder 17)
    - 1945, "What the Schools Can Learn from the Training Programs of the Armed Forces." May "Placement Tests as a means of Determining Advanced Standing at the University of Chicago." July "From School to College; Curriculum Experiment in the United States." July 21 "Extension of Responsibilities for Counseling and Guidance in Higher Institutions." September "Educational News and Editorial Comment." October "Trends in Safety Education at the Elementary Level." November (Box 56, Folder 18)
    - 1946, "Charles Hubbard Judd; 1873-1946." September (2 items) "The Role of University Departments of Education in the Preparation of School Administrations." October (Box 56, Folder 19)
    - 1947, "Major Issues in Education Today." February "Adult Education Is for Teachers, Too." November "A Place Where Teachers Learn." November "Proposals for Adults." November (Box 56, Folder 20)
    - 1948, "The Cooperative Study in General Education." January 1 "Should Every High School Develop a Core Curriculum?" January "Cooperation and Conflict in the Mental Development of the Child." April "How Can We Improve High-School Teaching?" September "Words That do Not Educate." November "Educability and the Schools." December "The Need for a More Comprehensive Formulation of Theory of Learning a Second Language." December (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - 1949-1952, "Trends in Professional Education." January "Better Teachers Are Coming." May "The Road to Better Appraisal." May "Trends in Teaching; How Research Is Affecting Our Understanding of the Learning Process." May Review of Social Work Education in the United States. December "The Evaluation of Instruction." February 20 "Discussion." [Racial and cultural relations.] Autumn 1952-Winter 1953 "Next Steps in Improving Secondary Education." December (Box 57, Folder 2)
    - 1953, "Facing Up to the Big Issues." January "The Leader of Major Educational Projects." [W.W. Charters.] February 11 "Helen Is Smarter Than Betsy." [Reporting to Parents.] March "The Core Curriculum." December "Leadership Role of the School Administrator in Curriculum and Instruction." December (Box 57, Folder 3)
    - 1954-1956, "Modern Aspects of Evaluation." November "Human Behavior; What Are the Implications for Education?" October "Study Center for Behavioral Scientists." March 9 "Recent Research Sheds Light on School." Relationships." May "What Is Behavioral Science?" August 10 "Clarifying the Role of the Elementary School." November "The Palo Alto Conference on Law and Behavioral Science." No. 3, 1956 (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - 1957-1959, "The Individual in Modern Society." February "The Place of the Social Sciences in the Libral Arts Curriculum." April "Scholarship and Career Education for the Correctional Service." Fall "Meeting the Challenge of the Gifted." The Elementary School Journal, November "The Education of Teachers; A Major Responsibility of Colleges and Universities." July "Emphasize Tasks Appropriate for the School." November "Conditions for Effective Learning." September "A Behavioral Scientist Looks at Medicine." October "Strengthening the Curriculum of the American Public Schools." October "Do We Need a `National Curriculum'? A Conference Report." November (Box 57, Folder 5)
    - 1960, "Policies and Strategy for Strengthening the Curriculum." February "Health Education Implications from the Behavioral Sciences." May-June 1960 "Science and the Seeking Mind." May "The Teaching Obligation." May "The Teaching Obligation and Typewriting." November (Box 57, Folder 6)
    - 1961, "The Learning Process." Spring "The Educational Potential of 4-H." June "The Committee on Personality Development in Youth." September "Educational Measurement; A Broad Perspective." September "Proposal for Research on Honors." October "The Social Sciences and Honors Programs; Possibilities for Research." October "Some Implications of Behavioral Science Research Regarding Group Influences on Individual Behavior." October (Box 57, Folder 7)
    - 1962-1963, "Specific Contributions of Research to Education." April "Where We Came Out." [Encyclopedia Britannica Conference on the Technological Order.] Fall "Education in a World of Change." September "Social Forces and Trends." September "Forces Redirecting Science Teaching." October "Implications of Behavioral Studies for Health Education." January "Evaluation in Teaching for Creativity." June (Box 57, Folder 8)
    - 1964-1965, "America Needs the Experimental College." January + 2 preprints "The Interrelationship of Knowledge." February "Evaluating the Elementary School." May "What Should High Schools Accomplish?" November "The Knowledge Explosion; Implications for Secondary Education." January "The Role of the Volunteer." Winter "Assessing the Progress of Education." September "Assessing Educational Progress." December (Box 57, Folder 9)
    - 1966, "Let's Clear the Air on Assessing Education." February "Importance of Innovations in Schools and Colleges." March "Opinions Differ." [Higher education and cybernation.] March "The Objectives and Plans for a National Assessment of Educational Progress." Spring "Assessing the Progress of Education." April "Perspective; Roaming the Behavioral Sciences." April "Frontiers in Industrial Arts Education." May-June "New Trends in Education." June "Assessing the Progress of Education in Science." September "How Can Engineering Education Increase Student Learning?" September "New Dimensions in Curriculum Development." September "What the Assessment of Education Will Ask." November (Box 57, Folder 10)
    - 1967, "National Educational Assessment; Pro and Con." January "A.A.S.A. Confuses Assessing with Testing, Contends Ralph Tyler." March "National Committee on Secondary Education; A Report." May "Current Status of the Project on Assessing the Progress of Education." Summer "Education Is Happening." August-September "National Assessment of Educational Progress." September "Needed Research in Mathematics Education." Fall "Contributions of the National Assessment to Instructional Improvement." October "Instructional Technology and the Behavioral Sciences." October "A Talk with Ralph Tyler." October (Box 57, Folder 11)
    - 1968, "Critique of the Issue on Educational and Psychological Testing." [Review of Educational Research] February "The Influence of the Curriculum and Teaching on the Development of Creativity." Spring "Purposes for Our Schools." December (Box 57, Folder 12)
    - 1969-1970, "National Assessment; Some Valuable By-Products for Schools." May "Curriculum for a Troubled Society." August "The Education of Health Personnel to Meet the Needs of the Child in Contemporary Society." January "Assessment; What Is It?" September "Curriculum Improvement in the University." November "National Assessment; A History and Sociology." December "Testing for Accountability." December (Box 57, Folder 13)
    - 1971-1973, "Recommendations for Action." [Urban education conference.] January "First Reports from the National Assessment." March "Theory and Practice; Bridging the Gap." May-June "Why Evaluate Education?" February "Conditions for Learning Religion." July-August "Assessing the Potential of Vicarious Experience in the Development of Children." October "What If the School Doesn't Have an Oil Well?" December 1972-January 1973 "Assessing Educational Achievement in the Affective Domain." Spring "The Father of Behavioral Objectives Criticizes Them; An Interview with Ralph Tyler." September "Ralph Tyler Discusses Behavioral Objectives." September-October (Box 57, Folder 14)
    - 1974, "The Federal Role in Education." Winter "Utilizing Research in Curriculum Development." February "Educational Supply and Manpower Needs in the Coming Decades." March "The National Assessment of Educational Progress." Spring "Concluding Observations and Recommendations." [Workshop on Action-Learning.] November (Box 57, Folder 15)